Guide to the Russell G. (R. G.) Vliet Papers
The Wittliff Collections
Russell G. (R. G.) Vliet Papers
1900-1986
1960-1984
The Wittliff Collections
Vliet, R. G. (Russell Gordon), 1929-1984
SWWC.034
22 Linear Feet
45 boxes
This collection consists of notes, outlines, drafts, typescripts, correspondence, subject files, photographs, newsclippings, artifacts, a scrapbook, legal, medical, and financial records.
Scope and Contents
Consisting of notes, outlines, drafts, typescripts, correspondence, subject files, photographs, newsclippings, artifacts, a scrapbook, legal, medical, and financial records, this material was created and maintained by R.G. Vliet, with the exception of some material maintained by his widow, Ann Vliet, after Mr. Vliet's death. Dates range from 1900-1990 (bulk 1960-1984).
This material documents the author's writing process and career, covering the various genres in which he worked, and demonstrating the creative overlap between these genres (plays, poems, and short stories worked into novels, for example). For each major work, extensive background notes, outlines, sketches, drafts, handwritten copies, and typescripts exist, showing details of the author's creative method. Of special interest are the research files, drafts, and correspondence relating to the author's final, and posthumously published, novel, Scorpio Rising.
Personal items include photographs, a large scrapbook, newsclippings, notebooks, medical, legal, and financial records, and several artifacts, such as clothing and eyeglasses. This material offers a perspective on the personal lives of R.G. and Ann Vliet.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchase, 1993
Biographical Note
Poet, novelist, playwright, and short story writer Russell G. Vliet was born in Chicago, on November 4, 1929. His father was a Naval medical officer, and the family lived in many parts of the U.S., largely in the south, and in American Samoa. R.G. Vliet attended Central High School (Class of 1948) in Texas City, Texas, just south of Houston, and attended Southwest Texas State University beginning in the Fall of 1948, where he wrote and acted in his own plays. While at the university, he met Vida Ann Rutherford, of New Braunfels, a fellow Speech and Drama major. The couple married on March 1, 1951, and had a daughter, Brooke, in 1957. The Vliets received their B.S. degrees in Education in 1952, and R.G. Vliet went on to complete his Master's at SWT with the thesis, "Experiment in lyric and dramatic verse", in 1953. Vliet then taught English for one year at Brown's School in Austin, and one year at Rock Springs High School in the Texas Hill Country. Even though many of Vliet's novels, plays, and poems would be set in Texas and would win awards from Texan literary institutions, Vliet would not live in Texas again, except for a six-month period near the end of his life, in 1983.
In 1955, Vliet went from teaching English to attending Yale University School of Drama, where he studied playwrighting with Robert Penn Warren and others for one and a half years. He left Yale to start his own writing career, which began with a string of award winning plays. In 1957, his play, "The Arid Spell", won the Wisconsin Award. In 1959, his play, "The Regions of Noon", was named Southeastern Theatre Conference New Play of the Year. In 1960, while working as a Ford Foundation Fellow, his play, "Rockspring", won the University of Nebraska Award. This play would later be worked into Vliet's first novel, of the same name. During this time, Vliet and his family lived in Pennsylvania, Connecticut, and Morelos, Mexico, traveling and relocating as his wife's college English teaching career, the family's financial mainstay, required.
In 1966, at the age of 37, Vliet published his first book of poetry, Events and Celebrations. It contained the poem "Clem Maverick: The Life and Death of a Country Music Singer", which would later be individually published by Shearer Publishing, accompanied by woodcut illustrations by Barbara Whitehead. His second book of poetry, The Man with the Black Mouth, was published in 1970. Each of these books of poetry won the Voertman Poetry Award from the Texas Institute of Letters.
From 1971 to 1982, Vliet wrote, and worked a small farm in Stamford, Vermont. He published his first novel, Rockspring, in 1974, at age 44, which sold only a few thousand copies. Despite the novel's relatively low sales, Rockspring earned Vliet $25,000 from the sale of movie rights to the work, the most money he would receive for any of his literary efforts. His 1977 novel, Solitudes, (later reprinted under the name Soledad ) won the Texas Institute of Letters Jesse Jones Award. At a time when large publishing houses rarely took on poetry, Random House published his next book of poetry, Water & Stone (1980). In 1983, he won a literary fellowship which allowed him to spend six months writing at the late J. Frank Dobie's ranch, Paisano. This brief period was essentially the only time Vliet spent in Texas after his schooldays and early teaching days. While there, he began writing what would be his last novel, Scorpio Rising.
Vliet was diagnosed with non-Hodgkins lymphoma in 1972, and after a brief illness, the disease went into remission. In 1982, Vliet learned that the lymphoma had come out of remission, and had taken a strong grip on his health. The following year, he was recognized with a Distinguished Alumni Award from his alma mater, Southwest Texas State University. Despite serious illness from chemotherapy as well as from the symptoms of the disease itself, Vliet continued work on his last novel, Scorpio Rising, completing it just days before his death. This novel, set in both Massachusetts and Texas, is widely considered to be his best. Russell Gordon Vliet died of lymphoma in North Adams, Massachusetts, in May, 1984.
Since his death, Vliet's novel Solitudes was reprinted by Texas Christian University Press as Soledad, (1986), and cited in James Ward Lee's Classics of Texas Fiction, in 1987. Rockspring was reprinted by Southern Methodist University (1992), the play "Regions of Noon" was published in William Martin's Texas Plays, (Southern Methodist University Press,1990), and Vliet's poetry will be featured in a forthcoming anthology edited by Dave Oliphant. Malcolm Cowley, who served as editor for Vliet and many other award-winning authors at Random House, describes Vliet's prose as "a joy and a continual surprise. There is nobody else with talent for evoking Texas as it was in the 1880s, nobody else who gives us the same sharp feeling for landscape, animals, birds, changing skies, and above all for people, as they lived out their solitary, violent lives full of kindness, resentments, and hardships accepted without complaint. Vliet's writing is close to becoming a national treasure."
Authors, American; Drama; Dramatists; Poetry; Theater; Literature; Vliet, R. G. (Russell Gordon), 1929-1984
- Works
  Series Desciption
  This series is arranged into the following sub-series: Novels, Plays, Poetry, Stories, Articles and Essays, Speeches, and Subject Files.
  - Novels, 1971-1984
    Sub-Series Description
    This subseries very clearly shows Vliet's process of writing from preliminary research through final product. It includes extensive background research files including files by subject containing clippings from newspapers and magazines, library call slips, color and black and white photographs, and handwritten notes. Following these research files are drafts of chapters handwritten in pencil, annotated typescripts, clean typescripts, and (minimal) correspondence. Perhaps most meticulously documented is the process of writing Scorpio Rising, Vliet's last novel, despite the fact that he was violently ill when writing it and died only one week after completing it. The author's widow, Ann Vliet, saw this novel through to publication.
    - Balcones (unfinished fourth novel), 1921-1976
      - 1920's Background research notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-6)
      - Notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 6a)
      - Library call slips for texts, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Adolf, Viola Ebel. Lisa's Texas Grandma. Boerne, Texas: Highland Press, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Call, Hughie. Golden Fleece. New York: Crown Publishers, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Happold, F.C. Mysticism. Middlesex, England: Penguin Books, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Patterson, Paul. Crazy Women in the Rafters. Norman: University of Oklahoma Press, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Thompson, Holland, ed. The Book of Knowledge: The Book of Texas. Dallas: The Grolier Society, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - The Daedalian. Denton: Senior Class of the College of Industrial Arts, 1922 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Balcones: A Narrative Sequence, undated
      - Unfinished Balcones and other published titles, undated (Box 3, Folder 1a)
    - A Friend in the Sahara (unpublished), undated
      - Typescript, undated (Box 3, Folder 2-3)
    - Medina (unpublished), undated
      - Second Medina rewrite castoffs, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Rockspring, 1974
      - Notes (including Spanish translation notes and color photos), undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - Manuscript, pencil draft, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - First typescript, annotated, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Working copy (typescript, annotated), undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - Carbon typescript, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - Galleys, annotated, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - Holograph pages, heavily annotated, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - Mock-up of final book, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Robert Renfield's "Maiden Voyage," a screenplay based on Vliet's Rockspring, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - Robert Renfield's "The Treasure," a screenplay based on Vliet's Rockspring, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Scorpio Rising, 1985
      - Background Research, circa 1980s
        - American Glossary of Architectural Terms (Box 5, Folder 2)
        - Birds (Box 5, Folder 3)
        - "Changling" (play by Middleton and Rowley) (Box 5, Folder 4-6)
        - Children's lore (Box 5, Folder 7)
        - Clothing (Box 5, Folder 8)
        - Factual data #2 (Box 5, Folder 9)
        - Factual data #3 (Box 6, Folder 1)
        - Flowers and plants (Box 6, Folder 2)
        - Greek masks (Box 6, Folder 3)
        - Houston (Box 6, Folder 4)
        - Insects (Box 6, Folder 5)
        - Land / Towns (including Rocksprings Graveyard, Kyle Graveyard, drawings of Alto Springs) (Box 7, Folder 1)
        - Literary notes (notes on specific works Vliet read relating them to S.R., authors such as Jung, Monod, more) (Box 7, Folder 2)
        - Minerals / Lichens (Box 7, Folder 3)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 7, Folder 4)
        - Music (Box 7, Folder 5)
        - Names (Box 7, Folder 6)
        - New Orleans (including train schedules) (Box 7, Folder 7)
        - Religions / Superstitions (Box 7, Folder 8)
        - Remedies and cures (Box 7, Folder 9)
        - Rivers / Canyons / Lakes (Box 7, Folder 10)
        - Scoliosis / Yellow Fever / Anthrax / Tuberculosis (Box 8, Folder 1)
        - Trains / Stations / Schedules (Box 8, Folder 2)
        - Words and Phrases (Box 8, Folder 3)
        - A Young Woman's Reading (Box 8, Folder 4)
        - Research citations (Box 8, Folder 5)
        - Sketches, Incidents (Box 8, Folder 5a)
        - Section I Notes (including 1981 letter to Mr. Lowe, and paper "The Nature and Education of a Poet", and notes on Section I handwritten in form of poetry, as well as a few typewritten annotated pages of text, 2 letters from "WS" 1980 at end) (Box 8, Folder 6)
      - Chapter drafts (handwritten and typed with corrections), circa 1980s
        - Chapter 1 (Box 8, Folder 7)
        - Chapter 4 (Box 8, Folder 8)
        - Chapter 5 (Box 8, Folder 9)
        - Chapter 6 (Box 8, Folder 10)
        - Chapter 7 (Box 9, Folder 1)
        - Chapter 8 (Box 9, Folder 2)
        - Chapter 9 (Box 9, Folder 3)
        - Chapter 10 (Box 9, Folder 4)
        - Chapter 11 (Box 9, Folder 5)
        - Chapter 12 (Box 10, Folder 1)
        - Chapter 15 (Box 10, Folder 2)
        - Chapter 1 (Box 10, Folder 3)
        - Chapter 18 (Box 10, Folder 4)
        - Chapter 19 (Box 10, Folder 5)
        - Chapter 20 (Box 10, Folder 6)
        - Chapter 21 (Box 10, Folder 7)
        - Chapter 22 (Box 10, Folder 8)
        - Chapter 23 (Box 10, Folder 9)
        - Chapter 24 (Box 10, Folder 10)
        - Unidentified Chapters (Box 11, Folder 1-4)
        - Section I Typescript (Box 11, Folder 41)
        - Complete pencil draft (Box 11, Folder 5)
        - Original ending (pencil draft) (Box 12, Folder 1)
        - Typescript rewrites (Box 12, Folder 2)
        - Typescript and 1984 letter from Ann Vliet to Random House (Box 12, Folder 4-5)
        - Uncorrected proof, annotated (Box 12, Folder 6)
        - Dust jacket and unbound signatures (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Solitudes (Soledad), 1977
      - Background (Box 13, Folder 1-2)
      - Literary notes (Box 13, Folder 3)
      - Factual data 1 (Box 13, Folder 4)
      - Factual data 2 (Box 13, Folder 5)
      - Notes (Box 13, Folder 6-7)
      - Drafts (fragments) (Box 14, Folder 1-2)
      - Rewrites (Box 14, Folder 3-4)
      - Cast-off pages (Box 14, Folder 5)
      - Manuscript (pencil draft) (Box 14, Folder 6-8)
      - "Copy 2 uncorrected" typescript (Box 15, Folder 1)
      - Annotated typescript [A] (Box 15, Folder 2-3)
      - Annotated typescript [B] (Box 15, Folder 4-5)
      - Annotated typescript [C] (Box 16, Folder 1-4)
      - Typescript [D] (Box 16, Folder 5-7)
      - Typescript [D] (Box 17, Folder 1)
      - "Revised typescript" (Box 17, Folder 2-3)
      - Pre-publication typescript (with final corrections) (Box 17, Folder 4-5)
      - Editor's mark-ups Section I (Box 18, Folder 1)
      - Editor's mark-ups Section II (Box 18, Folder 2)
      - Galleys (Box 18, Folder 3)
      - Second printing, marked-up by Vliet for reprint (Box 18, Folder 4)
      - "Material to be added to novel if reprinted" (Box 18, Folder 5)
      - Manuscripts used in revision of Soledad, 1982 (Box 18, Folder 6)
      - Annotated typescript of reprint (Box 19, Folder 1)
      - Annotated typescript of reprint (Box 19, Folder 2-4)
      - Reprint page proofs (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - Unidentified annotated typescript fragment, undated (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Plays, 1953-1980, undated
    Drafts of plays (mostly handwritten in pencil and annotated) and typescripts (mostly mimeographs or photocopies with annotations) are arranged in this subseries in alphabetical order. For reviews and further information regarding the author's plays, see Series II: Personal, Newsclippings.
    - Fragments, undated (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - "Amiddle the Fence", 1961 (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - "The Arid Spell", undated (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - "Billie", 1957 (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - "Farewell", undated (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - "A Friend in the Sahara", 1978, undated
      - Research notes (Box 20, Folder 6)
      - Scenario (Box 20, Folder 7)
      - Pencil draft (Box 20, Folder 8)
      - Typescript of copyrighted version, 1964 (Box 20, Folder 9-10)
      - Pencil draft: Rewriting of…, June 18, 1978 (Box 21, Folder 1)
      - Annotated typescripts (Box 21, Folder 2-3)
      - Cast-off pages (Box 21, Folder 4)
      - Typescripts (Box 21, Folder 5-7)
    - "High Intent in Arms" (presented at Southwest Texas State University), 1953
      - Annotated typescript (Box 21, Folder 8)
      - Play program (Box 21, Folder 9)
      - Research notes for play on Abraham Lincoln (untitled) (Box 21, Folder 10)
      - "The Progress of War" typescript (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - "The Regions of Noon", 1977-1982
      - Pencil draft (First and Third) (Box 22, Folder 2)
      - Pencil draft (Box 22, Folder 3)
      - Typescript and notes (Box 22, Folder 4)
      - Typescript (Box 22, Folder 5)
      - "Final draft", 1977 (Box 22, Folder 6)
      - Typescript, 1977 (Box 22, Folder 7)
      - "Final" typescript, undated (Box 22, Folder 8)
      - "Final" rewrite typescript, May 23-26, 1980 (Box 23, Folder 1-2)
      - Final typescript, 1982 (Box 23, Folder 3)
      - Photographs of production (Box 23, Folder 4)
    - "Rockspring", 1960
      - Manuscript (pencil draft) (Box 23, Folder 5)
      - Annotated typescript (Box 23, Folder 6)
      - Photographs of productions (University of Nebraska and Southwest Texas State University), both 1960 (Box 23, Folder 7)
      - Publicity (Box 23, Folder 8)
    - "Sweetly Sings the Mocker" (typescript), undated (Box 23, Folder 9)
    - "To Gettysburg" (typescript), 1962 (Box 23, Folder 10)
    - "Water & Stone" ("NOH Play"), undated
      - Draft manuscript (Box 23, Folder 11)
      - Typescript (Box 23, Folder 12)
  - Poetry, 1954-1983, undated
    Individual handwritten and typed poems, and hand-bound books of poetry, comprise this subseries. Many of the individual poems are accompanied by drafts, some are single copies. Individual poems are arranged alphabetically, followed by books of poetry, also arranged alphabetically. See also Series 2: Personal, Subseries C: Scrapbook, for early drafts of poetry.
    - Individual Poems, undated
      - "Ceremony" (Box 24, Folder 1)
      - "A Cloudy Day" (Box 24, Folder 2)
      - "Crystal Radio Song" (Box 24, Folder 3)
      - "Dogs Countless as Stars" (Box 24, Folder 4)
      - "Elemental Angel" (Box 24, Folder 5)
      - "Emily Dickinson" (Box 24, Folder 6)
      - "A Friend in Sahara" (Box 24, Folder 7)
      - "The Ghost" (Box 24, Folder 8)
      - [How, in silence…] (Box 24, Folder 9)
      - "Jet Plane" (Box 24, Folder 10)
      - "Mrs. McElroy" (Box 24, Folder 11)
      - [My heart…] (Box 24, Folder 12)
      - "Morir en el dia" (Box 24, Folder 13)
      - [The mountain floats in the air…] (Box 24, Folder 14)
      - "The Night Before the Day" (Box 24, Folder 15)
      - [An Old Man in the Orchard…] (Box 24, Folder 16)
      - [Un Viejo en la huerta…] (Box 24, Folder 17)
      - "The Opening Line" (Box 24, Folder 18)
      - "Passage" (drafts and notes) (Box 24, Folder 19)
      - "Penny Ballad for Elvious Ricks" (Box 24, Folder 20)
      - "Poetry" (Box 24, Folder 21)
      - "Scarecrow Girl" (Box 24, Folder 22)
      - "That Sense" (Box 24, Folder 23)
      - "This Face" (Box 24, Folder 24)
      - "To My Daughter" (drafts) (Box 24, Folder 25)
      - "To My Daughter" (printed copies) (Box 24, Folder 26)
      - [Twice I've been to the ocean…] (Box 24, Folder 27)
      - [When the heart stops, when the last…] (Box 24, Folder 28)
      - Untitled poem drafts and fragments (Box 24, Folder 29)
      - Untitled poem drafts and fragments ("Rejected") (Box 24, Folder 30)
    - Books of Poetry, 1966-1983, undated
      - Events and Celebrations, 1966
        - Unrevised proofs (galleys) (Box 24, Folder 31)
        - Author's annotated copy of hardbound edition (Box 24, Folder 32)
      - Water and Stone, 1980
        - Notes (Box 25, Folder 1-2)
        - Annotated typescript (Box 25, Folder 3)
        - Typescript (Box 25, Folder 4)
        - Galleys (Box 25, Folder 4a)
      - Clem Maverick, 1983
        - Notes (Box 25, Folder 5)
        - Country music cassettes (Box 25, Folder 6)
        - Country music 45 rpms (Box 25, Folder 7)
        - Magazines (Box 25, Folder 8-9)
        - Typescript (Box 26, Folder 1)
        - Dust jacket and signatures, 1983 (Box 26, Folder 2)
        - "Earplay" radio presentation of Clem Maverick, publicity and recordings (Box 26, Folder 3)
        - Clem Maverick and Water and Stone typescript (Box 26, Folder 3a)
      - Selected Poems (unpublished), undated
        - Original draft and photocopies (Box 26, Folder 4-8)
        - "Copy #2 Final version" (Box 26, Folder 9)
        - Deletions from Selected Poems (Box 26, Folder 10)
        - Photocopy for submission to publisher (Box 26, Folder 11)
        - Intermediate copy, hand bound (Box 27, Folder 1)
      - Collected Poems (Contains 66 of 101 poems written between August, 1954 and May 25, 1979) [unpublished]
        - Photocopy of workbook (Box 27, Folder 2)
      - Vliet's hand bound and annotated books of poetry, undated
        - Poetry 1 (Box 27, Folder 3)
        - Poetry 2 (Box 27, Folder 4)
        - Poetry 3 (Box 27, Folder 5)
        - Poetry 4 (Box 27, Folder 6)
        - Poetry 5 (Box 27, Folder 7)
        - Poetry 6 (Box 28, Folder 1)
        - Selected (Culled) Poems (Box 28, Folder 2)
        - Collected Poems (Box 28, Folder 3)
        - Passage and Water & Stone (Box 28, Folder 4)
        - Clem Maverick (Box 28, Folder 5)
        - Handmade book boxes (2) (Box 29)
  - Short Stories, 1957-1963, undated
    This subseries includes short stories such as "The Morning of the First Day" and "The Morning and the Evening of the First Day". Many are complete stories, some are fragments or are in draft form. Portions of these examples of Vliet's early prose would later be worked into the author's novels.
    - "The Ants" annotated typescript (Box 30, Folder 1)
    - "Dawn" as published in Southwest Review (Box 30, Folder 2)
    - "Eden" typescripts (Box 30, Folder 3)
    - Heroics and Cenotaph" manuscript and typescript (Box 30, Folder 4)
    - "The Journey" typescript (Box 30, Folder 5)
    - "The Morning of the First Day: Early prose and an epilogue – four stories" - Page proofs, 1959 (Box 30, Folder 6-7)
    - "The Morning and the Evening of the First Day: Early prose and an epilogue – four stories" - Typescript, 1963 (Box 30, Folder 8-9)
    - "Rhoda" (annotated typescript), 1957 (Box 30, Folder 10)
    - Unfinished/unidentified (Box 30, Folder 11)
  - Articles and Essays, 1960, undated
    Articles and essays in this subseries relate to Vliet's own writing process and influences. All are in typescript form and most have handwritten annotations.
    - "A Fable" Southern Theater News, Fall, 1960 (Box 30, Folder 12)
    - "A Sort of Preface" (Box 30, Folder 13)
    - "Early Reading Experiences" for the School Library Journal (Box 30, Folder 14)
    - "On Ritual in the Drama" (Box 30, Folder 15)
    - [Untitled] "I remember with joy my years…" (Box 30, Folder 16)
  - Speeches, 1978-1983, undated
    This subseries includes drafts and typescripts of four speeches which address Vliet's writing process and influences. Also included here is the author's acceptance speech for the 1978 Texas Institute of Letters Award received for his novel, Solitudes.
    - "A Correspondence of Forms", undated (Box 30, Folder 17)
    - "On a Literature of the Southwest: An Address" Acceptance speech for Texas Institute of Letters Award for novel, Solitudes, as printed in Texas Observer, April, 1978 (Box 30, Folder 18)
    - "South by West: The Nature of Education of the Poet", Therese Kayser Lindsay Address at Southwest Texas State University, October 26, 1978 (Box 30, Folder 19)
    - [Untitled] Original draft of talk at Texas Literary Traditions Symposium, LBJ Auditorium, Austin, Texas, March, 1983 (Box 30, Folder 20)
  - Subject Files, undated
    Handwritten and typed notes, clippings, and photocopies, arranged in alphabetical order by the author's subject categories, comprise the majority of this subseries. Also included are several folders of topographical and road maps of various Texas counties and other locations.
    - Animals (Box 31, Folder 1)
    - Articles (Box 31, Folder 2)
    - Authors (Box 31, Folder 2a)
    - Bibliographies (Box 31, Folder 3)
    - Factual data #1 (old) (Box 31, Folder 4)
    - Favored sources (Box 31, Folder 5)
    - Fish/amphibians (Box 31, Folder 6)
    - Maps (Box 31, Folder 7)
    - Market list (Box 31, Folder 8)
    - Mexican materials (Box 31, Folder 9)
    - Music (Box 31, Folder 10)
    - Oklahoma (Box 31, Folder 11)
    - People/faces (many marked with names from Scorpio Rising) (Box 31, Folder 12)